go hey guys coach bre and here um I
wanted to talk a little bit about the
deadling so there's a lot of uh experts
now who have been talking about the
concept of torque and I I think there's
more to be explained about this so
basically guys like Kelly starett I've
heard Mark Bel talk about when squatting
and even deadlifting you should be
creating torque and what this means is
um Kelly recommends pointing the feet
straight and as you come down you are
going to create hip external rotation um
the hips and also some of the lower leg
muscles can help do this but they say
screw your feet into the ground and when
you when you screw like if I was
standing on a force plate and I was
screwing my feet into the ground it
would measure lateral forces it's not
the same as just spreading your feet
you're twisting them as you come down
and flaring your legs out okay that's a
squat but in a deadlift they will
recommend this too to screw yourself
into position bend over pull the weight
up and uh I just want to offer a
different point of view most of the
powerlifters that I know and myself when
I line up for a deadlift um I don't
twist I don't I don't screw my feet in
the ground I don't create torque but I
did want to explain this concept a
minute um torque is just rotational
Force um it's turning Force so if I pick
if I perform a deadlift I am creating
torque I'm creating knee extension and
hip extension torque so you have to be
more specific you don't just you don't
just uh you don't need to create hip
external rotation torque in my opinion
when you're deadlifting because it's
just something you don't need to think
about when I'm going to deadlift I'm not
thinking screw my feet into position
because that's just one more thing to
think about I'm wasting energy twisting
this way when I want to be pulling the
weight upwards so again um some very
smart guys recommend this I think you
should experiment with it I've actually
gotten emails from people saying for the
first time you know I tried that and for
the first time I actually felt my glutes
working and
so um I think you should experiment with
it for some people it definitely helps
helps them use their glutes and use
their hips but other people don't need
it so much so give it a try and see what
you think but if you don't like it don't
be afraid to abandon it thanks for
watching